Contact

milasprouse@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/mila-sprouse-msn-rn-ccrn-28753a10 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Cardiology
Vascular Surgery
Interventional Cardiology

Languages

English (Full Professional) Filipino (Full Professional)

Honors-Awards

Cardiac Assist Account Manager Rookie of the Year - 2004

Cardiac Assist Account Manager of the Year - 2006

Trainer/Mentor -2008

Cardiac Assist Account Manager Plan Achievement Award - 2009

Cardiac Assist Account Manager Plan Achievement Award - 2010

Mila Sprouse MSN,RN, CCRN

Director of Nursing, Critical Care Services at Houston Methodist Willowbrook Hospital

Houston, Texas Area

Summary

Unstoppable, gritty/resilient, passionate about patient safety, fair & equitable, focused, plus strong leadership behaviors that drive engagement, commitment and creativity/innovation. Self directed and a very quick learner. Strong sense of self awareness, and ability to drive initiatives in place with success. Demonstrated ability to integrate business, financial and technology interests, lean processes into cohesive, driven, and focused operations. Built and led critical partnerships and alliances and finds value in divergent viewpoints. Leads multiple departments as a director of nursing in an acute care setting. Experienced as a director of clinical operations in the medical device industry.

Training: Extensive experience with complex critical care/CV therapies and tools. Highly knowledgeable in the area of critical care, cath lab, and CVOR arena. Multiple years of experience as a critical care educator, staff development educator, as an owner and lead presenter of a continuing education company in delivering education/presentation and syntheses of literature and studies, related to intraaortic balloon pumps, pVADs, ECMO, TAVI/TAVr, PCI, chest drains, advanced hemodynamic monitoring, CCRN/PCCN Reviews, Critical Care Courses, 12 Lead EKG, ACLS, CMC Reviews, CSC Reviews and medical device sales training. Multiple original presentation authorship.

Healthcare:

2019 Houston Chronicle's Top 150 Nurses Recipient2019 Outstanding Leadership Award Recipient - Houston MethodistWillowbrook Hospital

2019 - Recipient of the Innovation in Quality and Safety Award,Methodist System Peer Nominated Award

2019 - Top Performing Unit for the Prevention of CLABSI, Methodist System Quality & Patient Safety Performance Award

2019 - DLB Early Adopters, Methodist System Quality & Patient Safety Performance Awards

Sales: Excelled in sales
President's Club 2006
Sales Growth Award 2008
Multiple Awards YOY

Doctoral degree journey provided an invaluable experienced in research, literature searches, syntheses and analyses of data points. As a doctoral learner, is considered a highly trained researcher that is used to identifying and finding solutions to problems and continuously looks for and create solutions.

Experience

The Houston Methodist Willowbrook Hospital
Director of Nursing, Critical Care Services, Central Telemetry and
Vascular Department
August 2018 - Present (1 year 10 months)

Houston, Texas

In this position, I have a front-row seat of watching the transformation of my team & the successful execution of our collective vision. Inclusive leadership traits that I have developed from years of experience & continually reflecting on my interactions with others have proven to be effective in leading my teams. Inclusive leadership style takes on pieces from servant leadership, transformational, authentic, relational, & situational. It just happens to be my dissertation topic in my doctoral journey. My leader standard work includes:

- Listening & be in the moment with members of my team
- Being open & available for my team
- Collaborating effectively with medical team to roll out initiatives that benefit patients
- Director/townhall meeting with my team
- Mentoring as part of succession planning with those who have the traits and the skills that can replace me in my position
- Chair/Co-Chair hospital-wide committees effectively: identify OFIs, create solutions with stakeholders, plan, execute, and evaluate. Code Blue, Sepsis Committee, Critical Care Committee, Safe Patient Handling, Cardiac Surgery Committee, Mended Hearts. Also participates in quality, no harm, patient satisfaction, and others

- Led & supported rapid cycle process improvement initiatives:
- * Installation of the Digital Learning Board a unit transformation effort.

 It aims to provide resources to teams to become better collaborators & communicators. Results show decrease burnout, increase engagement, & improve patient quality outcomes
- * Manual proning initiative effective planning resulted in positive patient outcomes, fiscal advantage, & decrease strain on staffing resources
- * CVOR & ICU Throughput Handoff between two departments occurs in CVOR. The results show an increase in communication, physician/staff satisfaction, engagement, & patient quality outcomes
- * Cardiac Surgical Patient Outcomes Initiative Revision & execution of processes show a positive trajectory in patient outcomes

Maquet Getinge Group

14 years 10 months

Senior Field Trainer Cardiac Assist and Pulsion Hemodynamic Monitoring

November 2003 - August 2018 (14 years 10 months)

Maquet Medical Systems USA

Promoted to this position to assist in the development, coaching and training of new sales hires and tenured Clinical Account Managers and Sales Territory Managers on intra-aortic balloon pump therapy and Pulsion hemodynamics monitoring delivery systems in North America. Responsibilities include working in the field with sales & training management to perform gap assessments of the field sales team. Identify sales training needs, and assist in the development and delivery of relevant training courses or materials to close the gap on observed performance / selling deficiencies. Provide on-the-spot coaching and provide detailed, written summary of coaching plan / feedback that is delivered both to the sales reps and management team.

Additional responsibilities include in-house, classroom style product training on a broad host of topics including but not limited to: product feature/benefit training, product operation training, clinical applications, basic selling skills, presentation skills and policies and procedures. Create course content and updates relevant to assigned devices.

Participate in meetings that enhance the development of sales personnel.

Organize and collaborate learning centers during national conferences such as the AACN National Teaching Institute. Provide select presentation to the Society of Critical Care Medicine.

Principal Cardiac Assist Account Manager November 2003 - August 2018 (14 years 10 months)

Maquet Medical Systems USA

As Principal Cardiac Assist Account Manager excelled in sales, exceeding plans on a yearly basis. Extensive experience with complex critical care lifesaving therapies and tools. Highly knowledgeable in the area of the cardiac cath lab, cardiac care units, critical care, and cardiovascular OR arena. Collaborated and interacted with all levels of the healthcare team. Drove new strategies to increase business growth on intra-aortic balloon pumps and intra-aortic balloon catheters. Identified market opportunities to expand business strategies. Successful in building alliances among members of health care team to move the business forward. Involved in Grand Round activities with known cardiologists. Acted as a consultant for real-life troubleshooting of critically ill patients with cardiac assist devices at the bedside. Received awards for exceeding sales goals year after year.

Awards Received at Datascope/Getinge:

- * George Heller Award 2010 the most prestigious award in the company (Datascope) and is given to an individual in recognition of outstanding overall performance and professionalism and the recipient's knowledge and impact on the business
- * President's Club 2006 Achieved 114% Sales to Plan
- * Sales Growth Award 2008
- * Plan Achievement Award 2009
- * Plan Achievement Award 2010
- * Plan Achievement Award 2011
- * Plan Achievement Award 2012
- * Plan Achievement Award 2013
- * Converted territory market share to 100% in 3 years of work in the industry.
- * Cardiac Assist Account Manager Rookie of the Year 2004 Award given to a new account manager who showed exceptional qualities in understanding the business and a promising career within the company

Arjo

Director of Clinical Operations, North America November 2003 - August 2018 (14 years 10 months) Addison, Texas

Director of Clinical Operations, North America

As Director of Clinical Operations, responsible for designing and executing clinical projects/programs for the organization. Manages the delivery of clinical trials, overseeing trials, site selection, and overall trial oversight to completion.

Additionally, identifies accounts that benefit from the metrics of each program. Gather, extract, analyze, interpret data and create clinical evidence supporting the efficacy of each product. Also, focuses on establishing and developing relationships with KOLs.

As Director of Clinical Services/Regional Manager had operational responsibility for leading the Clinical Team. Ensured effective execution of established strategic goals. Supported the development of marketing and sales strategies by providing clinical expertise related to Critical Care, and Safe Patient Handling. Implemented processes to enhance productivity with the same amount of resources through critical analysis of work efficiency, reduction of expenses, increased in workflow and created a culture of accountability, responsibility, and awareness of quality and regulatory requirements by the FDA.

Kingwood Medical Center

Nurse Manager (Role is now Director of Critical Care) - Critical Care May 2001 - November 2003 (2 years 7 months)

Kingwood, Texas

Led & managed multiple departments (Intensive Care Unit, Telemetry & Intermediate Care Unit)

Ensured that department staff delivered quality nursing care

Directly participated in the Joint Commission rounds and successfully passed

Joint Commission requirements.

Collaborated with physicians and senior management to enhance delivery of care to patients.

Met budgetary constraints to achieve financial goals for the managed departments and facility.

Evaluated employees' training needs and consulted with Staff Development to plan and administer training to meet JCHAO requirements.

Attended and participated hospital-wide committees led by physicians and senior management to formulate a plan to meet CMS Core Measures.

Executed plans that resulted in better patient outcomes and patient safety. Initiated best practices model in the intensive care unit and drove the interest in certification and education.

Managed at least 78 full-time employees in the intensive care unit, telemetry, and intermediate unit.

Spring Branch Medical Center Staff Nurse (Charge Nurse - Alternate) Critical Care March 1995 - January 1997 (1 year 11 months)

SICU

Responsibilities included but not limited to taking care of critically ill patients in the CCU/SICU. Provided education for ICU personnel on IABP, 12 Lead EKG, CPR, ACLS, VADs and other critical care topics.

Sought after for clinical expertise and was involved in multiple committees that affects patient care.

Dr. Raymond Waters Cardiovascular Group Physician's Assistant June 1991 - June 1994 (3 years 1 month) Bayonet Point

Assessed and executed medical treatment of cardiac patients pre and post open-heart surgery. Conducted history and physical for newly admitted patients and patients going for open heart surgery, and developed a plan of care for patients pre and post op. Collaborated with cardiac surgeon and cardiologists regarding care of the patients pre and post open heart.

Regional Medical Center Bayonet Point
Critical Care Educator/Staff Development/Charge Nurse Cardiac
Surgical ICU
June 1989 - May 1994 (5 years)

Cardiac Surgical ICU

Integral part of the building process of a new and successful heart program doing 1200 plus OHS a year.

Maintained adequate staffing. Mentored new charge nurses and preceptors. Answered to the Director of Cardiac Surgical Unit in relation to maintaining budget within the department

Took care of a variety of patients post open heart with IABP, VAD, ventilators and others.

Developed best practices in post open heart patients and drove the certification process within the unit. Started a certification review within the unit.

Assessed educational needs of the entire employees of the hospital, then planned and implemented educational training with management collaboration to comply with JCHAO requirements. Made recommendations to Senior Management and Human Resources based on educational performance of an employee. Maintained record keeping for audit purposes. Provided orientation to new employees twice a month. Coordinated orientation program with numerous head departments to have a seamless orientation program delivered to new employees. Conducted BLS and ACLS programs to hospital

employees. Attended meetings with other department heads to obtain input to how we can improve our orientation end educational training for hospital personnel.

Assessed, planned and implemented a 12-week critical care course program (three times a year) for our critical care personnel (CSU, ICU, CCU, CCL, CVOR and ER). Monitored progress of critical care personnel through meetings and completion of established competencies.

Odessa Medical Center Assistant Manager/Charge Nurse/Staff Nurse SICU/CVICU 1987 - 1989 (2 years)

Odessa Texas

Responsibilities included care of critically ill patient in the unit as well as orientation of new personnel in the ICU, was utilized as a speaker for the critical care courses.

Sought after for involvement in hospital committees and represented organization to meetings in the community because of attitude, confidence and knowledge of anything related to health.

Mercy Regional Medical Center Staff Nurse 1986 - 1987 (1 year) San Angelo, Texas

Victoria Regional Medical Center Charge Nurse - ICU 1985 - 1986 (1 year) Victoria Texas

Maverick County Hospital District Charge Nurse November 1982 - 1984 (2 years) Eagle Pass, Texas

Delgado General Hospital Staff Nurse - NICU 1980 - 1982 (2 years) Quezon City, Philippines

Education

Grand Canyon University

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Doctor of Education in Organizational Leadership with an Emphasis in Health Care Administration · (2014 - 2018)

Grand Canyon University

Master's Degree, Nursing · (2011 - 2013)

Colegio San Agustin-Bacolod Bachelor's Degree, Nursing · (1976 - 1980)